[
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The first session of Constituent Assembly was held on",
        "answer": "9th December 1946",
        "choices": [
            "9th December 1946",
            "15th August 1947",
            "26th November 1949",
            "26th January 1946"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Indian Constitution was adopted by the Constituent Assembly on",
        "answer": "26th Novemeber 1949",
        "choices": [
            "26th Novemeber 1949",
            "26th Novemeber 1950",
            "26th January 1950",
            "15th August 1949"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "January 26 was selected as the date for the inaugaration of the Constitution, because",
        "answer": "The Congress had observed it as the Independence Day in 1930",
        "choices": [
            "The Congress had observed it as the Independence Day in 1930",
            "It was considered to be an auspicious day",
            "On that day the Quit India Movement was started in 1942",
            "MK Gandhi returned to India on that day"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who of the following was the chairman of the Provincial Constitution Committee of the Constituent Assembly of India",
        "answer": "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
        "choices": [
            "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Bhim Rao Ambedkar",
            "K. M. Munshi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was the labour Minister in Jawaharlal Nehru's Provisional Government?",
        "answer": "Jagjivan Ram",
        "choices": [
            "Jagjivan Ram",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Aruna Asaf Ali",
            "C. Rajgopalachari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Indian Constitution was adopted by",
        "answer": "Constituent Assembly",
        "choices": [
            "Constituent Assembly",
            "British Parliament",
            "Governor-General",
            "Indian Parliament"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Constitution Day of India is celebrated on",
        "answer": "26th Novemeber",
        "choices": [
            "26th Novemeber",
            "26th January",
            "15th August",
            "14th August"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was the President of Indian National Congress at the time of partition of India?",
        "answer": "J. B. Kripalani",
        "choices": [
            "J. B. Kripalani",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
            "C. Rajgopalachari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "In Indian political system which one is supereme?",
        "answer": "The Constitution",
        "choices": [
            "The Constitution",
            "The Supreme Court",
            "The President",
            "The Parliament"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following subject lies in the concurrent list?",
        "answer": "Education",
        "choices": [
            "Education",
            "Police",
            "Defence",
            "Agriculture"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Constitution Tenth schedule relates to",
        "answer": "Anti-Defection Law",
        "choices": [
            "Anti-Defection Law",
            "National Language of India",
            "Administration of SC and ST Area",
            "Judicial Review"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Land Reform comes under the subjects of",
        "answer": "State List",
        "choices": [
            "State List",
            "Union List",
            "Concurrent List",
            "National List"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is not a part in the Eleventh Schedule of the Constitution?",
        "answer": "Rural Sports",
        "choices": [
            "Rural Sports",
            "Libraries",
            "Fuel and Fodder",
            "Technical Training"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What was the duration in the making of the Indian Constitution?",
        "answer": "2 years 11 monts and 18 days",
        "choices": [
            "2 years 11 monts and 18 days",
            "1 years 11 monts and 18 days",
            "3 years 11 monts and 18 days",
            "2 years 10 monts and 18 days"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The provision of amending the constitutional provision is given in",
        "answer": "Part XX Article 368",
        "choices": [
            "Part XX Article 368",
            "Part XIX Article 356",
            "Part XX Article 356",
            "Part XXI Article 368"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which one of the following characterstics is not true for unitary form of Government?",
        "answer": "Ideal for large countries",
        "choices": [
            "Ideal for large countries",
            "Flexible",
            "Swift Decision",
            "Uniformity of Laws"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Democracy of India is based on the fact that",
        "answer": "Public enjoys the right to choose and change the Government",
        "choices": [
            "Public enjoys the right to choose and change the Government",
            "Fundamental Rights have been provided",
            "The Constitution is written",
            "Directive Principles of State policy have been provided for here"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which one of the following statements is correct regarding parliamentary form of government?",
        "answer": "Executive is responsible to the legislature",
        "choices": [
            "Executive is responsible to the legislature",
            "The legislature is responsible to Executive",
            "The Legislative and the Executive are independent",
            "The Legislature is responsible to Judiciary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the nature of the Indian Constitution",
        "answer": "Federal in nature but unitary in spirit",
        "choices": [
            "Federal in nature but unitary in spirit",
            "Federal",
            "Unitary",
            "Parliamentary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "After Independence, in which year were the Indian states reorganised on the linguistic basis?",
        "answer": 1956,
        "choices": [
            1956,
            2000,
            1947,
            1950
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Chief Minister of Union Territory, where such a setup exists, is appointed by the",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Governor",
            "Lieutenant Governor",
            "Chief Justice of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Creation of a new state requires which majority for Consitutional Amendment.",
        "answer": "Simple",
        "choices": [
            "Simple",
            "Two-third",
            "Three-fourth",
            "Two-third plus ratification by half of all states"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Delhi is a/an",
        "answer": "Union Territory",
        "choices": [
            "Union Territory",
            "State",
            "Autonomous Council",
            "Dominion"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Sikkim became an associate state of India under",
        "answer": "35th Amendment",
        "choices": [
            "35th Amendment",
            "45th Amendment",
            "42nd Amendment",
            "36th Amendment"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "On which day Sikkim gained full statehood in India",
        "answer": "16th May 1975",
        "choices": [
            "16th May 1975",
            "15th May 1975",
            "16th June 1975",
            "15th July 1975"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year did the state of Jharkhand come into existence?",
        "answer": 2000,
        "choices": [
            2000,
            1975,
            1956,
            1987
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Bihar as an Indian State was formed in ",
        "answer": 1912,
        "choices": [
            1912,
            1956,
            1987,
            1911
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The phrase equality before law used in Article 14 of the Indian Constitution has been borrowed from the Constitution of",
        "answer": "Britain",
        "choices": [
            "Britain",
            "USA",
            "France",
            "Canada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The phrase equality protection of law used in Article 14 of the Indian Constitution has been borrowed from the Constitution of",
        "answer": "USA",
        "choices": [
            "USA",
            "Britain",
            "France",
            "Canada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "From which country, the Indian Constitution has taken reference for the idea of the Fundamental Rights?",
        "answer": "United States of America",
        "choices": [
            "United States of America",
            "Ireland",
            "United Kingdom",
            "Canada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is given the power to enforce the Fundamental Rights by the Constitution?",
        "answer": "The Supreme Court and High Courts",
        "choices": [
            "The Supreme Court and High Courts",
            "All Courts in India",
            "The Parliament",
            "The President"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is meant by Rule of Law",
        "answer": "One act for all and one judiciary for all",
        "choices": [
            "One act for all and one judiciary for all",
            "One act for all and one state for all",
            "One state for all and one judicary for all",
            "All acts for one and one judiciary for all"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The description of Fundamental Rights for the Indian cititzens is in",
        "answer": "Article 12 to 35",
        "choices": [
            "Article 12 to 35",
            "Article 25 to 50",
            "Article 16 to 40",
            "Article 15 to 39"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Supreme Court's judgement of Indra Sawhney vs Union of India Case is related to which issue?",
        "answer": "Regarding OBC reservation in Government Employment",
        "choices": [
            "Regarding OBC reservation in Government Employment",
            "Doctrine of Basic Structure of Constitution",
            "Reservation on promotion of SC",
            "Extended reservation for ST"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which article of the Constitution of India is related with the Freedom of Press.",
        "answer": "Article 19",
        "choices": [
            "Article 19",
            "Article 20",
            "Article 21",
            "Article 22"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following can a court issue for enforcement of the Fundamental Rights?",
        "answer": "Writ",
        "choices": [
            "Writ",
            "Decree",
            "Ordinance",
            "Bill"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is not a fundamental right?",
        "answer": "Right to Property",
        "choices": [
            "Right to Property",
            "Right to Constitutional Remedy",
            "Right to Peaceful Assembly",
            "Right to free movement all over the country"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Supreme Court has held that hoisting the National Flag atop the private buildings is a fundamental right of every citizen under",
        "answer": "Article 19",
        "choices": [
            "Article 19",
            "Article 14",
            "Article 21",
            "Article 25"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following rights conferred by the Constitution of India is also available to non-citizens?",
        "answer": "Right to Constitutional Remedies",
        "choices": [
            "Right to Constitutional Remedies",
            "Freedom of Speech",
            "Freedom to move and settle in any part of the country",
            "Freedom to accquire property"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "When was the Right to Education added through the amendment in the Constitution of India?",
        "answer": "1st April 2010",
        "choices": [
            "1st April 2010",
            "1st August 2010",
            "2nd October 2010",
            "1st December 2010"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Untouchability is abolished by which article of the Indian Constitution?",
        "answer": "Article 17",
        "choices": [
            "Article 17",
            "Article 19",
            "Article 15",
            "Article 14"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which part of the Indian Constitution contains the Directive Principles of State Policy?",
        "answer": "Part IV",
        "choices": [
            "Part IV",
            "Part III",
            "Part V",
            "Part VI"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "How are Directive Principles of State Policy different from Fundamental Rights?",
        "answer": "DPSPs are not enforceable while Fundamental Rights are enforceable",
        "choices": [
            "DPSPs are not enforceable while Fundamental Rights are enforceable",
            "DPSPs are enforceable by courts, while Fundamental Rights are not.",
            "DPSPs are not part of Constitution while Fundamental Rights are",
            "DPSPs are part of Constitution while Fundamental Rights are not"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The concept of welfare state included in the Constitution of India in the",
        "answer": "Directive Principles of State Policy",
        "choices": [
            "Directive Principles of State Policy",
            "Fourth Schedule of the Constitution",
            "Fundamental Rights",
            "Preamble of Constitution"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Panchayat Raj System in India is laid down under",
        "answer": "Directive Principles of State Policy",
        "choices": [
            "Directive Principles of State Policy",
            "Fundamental Rights",
            "Fundamental Duties",
            "Election Commission Act"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Ministry of Panchayati Raj was created in the Central Government of India in",
        "answer": 2004,
        "choices": [
            2004,
            2001,
            2000,
            2003
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which one of the following Articles directs the State to organise the Panchayats?",
        "answer": "Article 40",
        "choices": [
            "Article 40",
            "Aritcle 50",
            "Article 33",
            "Article 36"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The concept of Directive Principles of State Policy in the Indian Constitution was borrowed from the Constitution of",
        "answer": "Ireland",
        "choices": [
            "Ireland",
            "Switzerland",
            "England",
            "United States of America"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Fundamental Duties are laid down in",
        "answer": "42nd Amendment",
        "choices": [
            "42nd Amendment",
            "43rd Amendment",
            "40th Amendment",
            "39th Amendment"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The 10 commandments, which were added in 42nd Amendment Act in Constitution of India, are called as ",
        "answer": "Fundamental Duties",
        "choices": [
            "Fundamental Duties",
            "Fundamental Rights",
            "Panchayati Raj Principles",
            "Directive Principles of State Policy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which one of the following is a Fundamental Duty in India?",
        "answer": "To value and preserve the rich heritage of our composite culture",
        "choices": [
            "To value and preserve the rich heritage of our composite culture",
            "Separation of judiciary from executive",
            "Free and compulsory education",
            "Abolition of Untouchability"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Electoral College for the election of the President of India consits of",
        "answer": "All elected members of both members of Parliament and elected members of the State Legislative Assemblies",
        "choices": [
            "All elected members of both members of Parliament and elected members of the State Legislative Assemblies",
            "All the elected members of the Rajya Sabha",
            "All the elected members of the Lok Sabha",
            "All the members of the State Legislative Assemblies"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "If there is any dispute regarding the Presidential election, it can be referred to",
        "answer": "Supreme Court of India",
        "choices": [
            "Supreme Court of India",
            "Attorney General of India",
            "Parliament",
            "Special Tribunal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The president of India can be removed from his post by",
        "answer": "Parliament",
        "choices": [
            "Parliament",
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "The Prime Minister of India",
            "Lok Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "If the position of President and Vice-President are vacant, who officiates as the President of India?",
        "answer": "Chief Justice of India",
        "choices": [
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Speaker of Lok Sabha",
            "Chairman of Rajya Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Indian President is eligible for re-election for how many times?",
        "answer": "Any number of times",
        "choices": [
            "Any number of times",
            "Once",
            "Twice",
            "Thrice"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who is the Executive Head of State in India?",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Leader of the Opposition",
            "Chief Secretary, Government of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who of the following has been vested with the executive powers  of the central government under the constitution of India?",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Central Cabinet",
            "All of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "President of India exercises his powers",
        "answer": "either directly or through officers subordinate to him",
        "choices": [
            "either directly or through officers subordinate to him",
            "through ministers",
            "through Prime Minister",
            "through Cabinet"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The President",
        "answer": "is a part of Parliament",
        "choices": [
            "is a part of Parliament",
            "is not a part of parliament",
            "is a part of parliament and sits in the parliament",
            "can vote in parliament"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Constitution doesn't empower the President of India with the right of",
        "answer": "Appointment of Chief Minister in states",
        "choices": [
            "Appointment of Chief Minister in states",
            "Appointment of Prime Minister",
            "Being the supreme commander of Defence Forces",
            "Executing emergency in any part of the country"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The first President of Independent India - Rajendra Prasad belonged to which state",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Andhra Pradesh",
            "Tamil Nadu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was among the following to receive first Bharat Ratna?",
        "answer": "Sarvapalli Radhakrishnan",
        "choices": [
            "Sarvapalli Radhakrishnan",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Lal Bahadur Shastri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "A bill presented in Parliament becomes an Act after",
        "answer": "the President has given his assent",
        "choices": [
            "the President has given his assent",
            "It is passed by both the houses of Parliament",
            "the Prime Minister has signed it",
            "the Supreme Court has declared it to be within the competence of the Union-Parliament"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following had been the first unopposed and unanimously elected President of India?",
        "answer": "Neelam Sanjeeva Reddy",
        "choices": [
            "Neelam Sanjeeva Reddy",
            "Savapalli Radhakrishnan",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Zakir Hussain"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the minimum age to be eligible for contesting election of President in India?",
        "answer": "35 years",
        "choices": [
            "35 years",
            "25 years",
            "32 years",
            "21 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the minimum age to be eligible for contesting election of Vice-President in India?",
        "answer": "35 years",
        "choices": [
            "35 years",
            "25 years",
            "32 years",
            "21 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "To whom does the President of India address his resignation letter?",
        "answer": "Vice-President",
        "choices": [
            "Vice-President",
            "Chief Justice",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Speaker of Lok Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "To whom does the Vice-President of India address his resignation letter?",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Chief Justice",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Speaker of Rajya Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who is the ex-officio Chairman of the Rajya Sabha?",
        "answer": "Vice-President",
        "choices": [
            "Vice-President",
            "President",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Chief Justice of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Electoral College for the 17th Vice Presidential Election of India for 2025 consists of how many members?",
        "answer": "788 members",
        "choices": [
            "788 members",
            "543 members",
            "245 members",
            "565 members"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The serial number of next Vice-President of India will be",
        "answer": "17th",
        "choices": [
            "17th",
            "16th",
            "15th",
            "18th"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Council of Ministers is responsible to the",
        "answer": "Lok Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Lok Sabha",
            "President",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Rajya Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Council of Ministers shall hold office during the pleasure of the",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Speaker of Lok Sabha",
            "Chief Justice of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Prime Minister of India is responsible to the",
        "answer": "Lok Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Lok Sabha",
            "President",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Rajya Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who administers the oaths of office and secrecy to Prime Minister?",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "Speaker of Lok Sabha",
            "Vice-President"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who administers the oaths of office and secrecy to Vice-President?",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "Speaker of Rajya Sabha",
            "Prime Minister"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who administers the oaths of office and secrecy to the President?",
        "answer": "Chief Justice of India",
        "choices": [
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "Vice-President",
            "Speaker of Rajya Sabha",
            "Prime Minister"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The word Matrimandal (Cabinet) is mentioned is which article?",
        "answer": "Article 352",
        "choices": [
            "Article 352",
            "Article 356",
            "Article 75",
            "Article 74"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who is the highest Civil Services Officers of the Central Government?",
        "answer": "Cabinet Secretary",
        "choices": [
            "Cabinet Secretary",
            "Attorney General of India",
            "Home Secretary",
            "Finance Secretary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Constitutional Amendment Act resitricted the size of the Council of Ministers to 15 percent of the total members of the Lok Sabha?",
        "answer": "91st Amendment, 2003",
        "choices": [
            "91st Amendment, 2003",
            "95th Amendment, 2009",
            "93rd Amendment, 2005",
            "90th Amendment, 2002"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who advises the Government of India on legal matters?",
        "answer": "Attorney General",
        "choices": [
            "Attorney General",
            "Comptroller & Auditor General",
            "Chief Justice of the Supreme Court",
            "Chairman, Law Commission"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which officer of the Government of India has the right to take part in the proceedings of Parliament of India even though he is not a member?",
        "answer": "Attorney General",
        "choices": [
            "Attorney General",
            "Comptroller & Auditor General",
            "Vice-President",
            "Election Commissioner"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who advises the State Government on legal matters?",
        "answer": "Advocate-General",
        "choices": [
            "Advocate-General",
            "Attorney General",
            "Solicitor General",
            "Chief Justice of the High Court"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Parliament's expenditure is controlled by the ",
        "answer": "Comptroller & Auditor General",
        "choices": [
            "Comptroller & Auditor General",
            "President",
            "NITI Aayog",
            "Finance Commission"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Lok Sabha can be dissolved before the completion of its term",
        "answer": "by the president on the recommendation of the Prime Minister",
        "choices": [
            "by the president on the recommendation of the Prime Minister",
            "at the discretion of the President",
            "at the discretion of the Prime Minister",
            "at the discretion of the speaker of Lok Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the minimum age laid down for a person to seek election to the Lok Sabha?",
        "answer": "25 years",
        "choices": [
            "25 years",
            "30 years",
            "35 years",
            "20 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the minimum age laid down for a member of the Parliament?",
        "answer": "25 years",
        "choices": [
            "25 years",
            "30 years",
            "35 years",
            "20 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the minimum age laid down for a member of the Rajya Sabha?",
        "answer": "30 years",
        "choices": [
            "30 years",
            "25 years",
            "35 years",
            "20 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Generally how many sessions are there in the Lok Sabha?",
        "answer": "Three",
        "choices": [
            "Three",
            "Two",
            "Four",
            "Five"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "A candidate of Lok Sabha poll loses his security amount if he/she does not get",
        "answer": "one-sixth of valid votes",
        "choices": [
            "one-sixth of valid votes",
            "one-third of valid votes",
            "one-fourth of valid votes",
            "one-fifth of valid votes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The state-wise allocation of seats in Lok Sabha is based on the 1971 Census. Up to which year does this remain intact?",
        "answer": 2026,
        "choices": [
            2026,
            2025,
            2031,
            2047
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Presently the number of seats each state in Lok Sabha is allotted on the basis of",
        "answer": "Census of 1971",
        "choices": [
            "Census of 1971",
            "Census of 1951",
            "Census of 1961",
            "Census of 1981"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Fifth Schedule deals with the governance and protection of which specific group of people?",
        "answer": "Scheduled Tribes",
        "choices": [
            "Scheduled Tribes",
            "Scheduled Castes",
            "Religious Minorities",
            "Linguistic Minorities"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "In which Article of the Constitution of India was the provision for reservation of scheduled castes in Lok Sabha made?",
        "answer": "Article 330",
        "choices": [
            "Article 330",
            "Article 331",
            "Article 332",
            "Article 333"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Session of Lok Sabha is called for at least",
        "answer": "two times in a year",
        "choices": [
            "two times in a year",
            "three times in a year",
            "once in a year",
            "four times in a year"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which State sends the largest number of members in Lok Sabha?",
        "answer": "Uttar Pradesh",
        "choices": [
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Bihar",
            "West Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "So long as the representation in Lok Sabha is concerned, which states rank second and third?",
        "answer": "Maharashtra & West Bengal",
        "choices": [
            "Maharashtra & West Bengal",
            "Bihar & Maharashtra",
            "Madhya Pradesh & Tamil Nadu",
            "Bihar & Tamil Nadu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "First General Election of Lok Sabha was held in",
        "answer": 1952,
        "choices": [
            1952,
            1950,
            1946,
            1947
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who is the leader of the Lok Sabha?",
        "answer": "Prime Minister",
        "choices": [
            "Prime Minister",
            "President",
            "Speaker",
            "Whip"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "A seat of an MP can be declared vacant if he absents himself from the house for a continous period of",
        "answer": "60 days",
        "choices": [
            "60 days",
            "30 days",
            "45 days",
            "90 days"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Speaker of the Lok Sabha is elected by",
        "answer": "all members of Lok Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "all members of Lok Sabha",
            "all members of parliament",
            "public directly",
            "the members of party in majority"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Attorney General of India is appointed by the",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Law Minister",
            "Speaker of the Lok Sabha",
            "Prime Minister"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Rajya Sabha consits of",
        "answer": "250 members of which 12 are nominated",
        "choices": [
            "250 members of which 12 are nominated",
            "280 members of which 20 are nominated",
            "275 members of which 18 are nominated",
            "252 members of which 12 are nominated"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Maximum members in The Lok Sabha",
        "answer": 550,
        "choices": [
            550,
            530,
            543,
            545
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Representation of States in Council of States is based on",
        "answer": "ratio of their Population",
        "choices": [
            "ratio of their Population",
            "ratio of their revenue",
            "ratio of their area",
            "equal for all states"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Member of Rajya Sabha is elected for",
        "answer": "6 years",
        "choices": [
            "6 years",
            "5 years",
            "4 years",
            "life long"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Member of Lok Sabha is elected for",
        "answer": "5 years",
        "choices": [
            "5 years",
            "6 years",
            "4 years",
            "life long"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "According to our Constitution, the Rajya Sabha",
        "answer": "is not subject to dissolution",
        "choices": [
            "is not subject to dissolution",
            "is dissolved once in two years",
            "is dissolved once in five years",
            "is dissolved once in six years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Right to dissolve the Rajya Sabha is vested in",
        "answer": "None of these",
        "choices": [
            "None of these",
            "President",
            "Vice-President",
            "Supreme Court"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The number of members nominated by the President in Rajya Sabha is",
        "answer": 12,
        "choices": [
            12,
            10,
            11,
            20
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "In which House is the presiding officer not a member of that House?",
        "answer": "Rajya Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Rajya Sabha",
            "Lok Sabha",
            "Vidhan Sabha",
            "Vidhan Parishad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Under which Article, the speaker can allow any member of the House to speak in his/her mother tongue?",
        "answer": "Article 120",
        "choices": [
            "Article 120",
            "Article 110",
            "Article 122",
            "Article 115"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What can be the maximum interval between the two consecutive sessions of Parliament?",
        "answer": "six months",
        "choices": [
            "six months",
            "12 months",
            "3 months",
            "9 months"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Zero Hour in political jargon refers to",
        "answer": "Question-Answer Session",
        "choices": [
            "Question-Answer Session",
            "Suspended Motion",
            "Adjourned Time",
            "Day when no business in parliament is done"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Joint session of both Houses of Parliament is concerned ",
        "answer": "to discuss and pass sucha a bill where both Houses have different opinion",
        "choices": [
            "to discuss and pass sucha a bill where both Houses have different opinion",
            "for the election of the President of India",
            "for the election of the vice-president of India",
            "to pass the bill relating to the amendment of Constitution"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Money Bill can be presented",
        "answer": "Only in Lok Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Only in Lok Sabha",
            "Only in Rajya Sabha",
            "In both the Houses",
            "in joint meeting of both the Houses"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Of the following statements, which one is not correct?",
        "answer": "Money bill is introduced in the Rajya Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Money bill is introduced in the Rajya Sabha",
            "The Rajya Sabha is powerless in money matters",
            "The Rajya Sabha has to pass the Money Bill within 14 days after it has been passed by the Lok Sabha",
            "The Rajya Sabha may pass or return the Money Bill with some recommendations to the Lok Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Vote on Account is meant for",
        "answer": "Appropriating funds pending passing of budget",
        "choices": [
            "Appropriating funds pending passing of budget",
            "vote on the report of CAG",
            "to meet unforeseen expenditure",
            "Budget"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the object of Cut Motion",
        "answer": "to move a proposal to reduce expenditure in the Budget proposals",
        "choices": [
            "to move a proposal to reduce expenditure in the Budget proposals",
            "to put check on the policies of the Government",
            "to stop the functioning of ruling party",
            "rejection of complete financial dealings of the Government"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Public Accounts Committee submits its report to",
        "answer": "Speaker of the Lok Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Speaker of the Lok Sabha",
            "Comptroller & Auditor General",
            "Prime Minister",
            "President"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The split system in the Indian Administration relates to",
        "answer": "Policy / Implementation",
        "choices": [
            "Policy / Implementation",
            "Audit / Accounts",
            "Union / States",
            "All India Service / Central Service"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Collegium System in India is primarily related to:",
        "answer": "Appointment and transfer of judges",
        "choices": [
            "Appointment and transfer of judges",
            "Appointment of Governors",
            "Appointment of Election Commissioners",
            "Appointment of Lokpal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following constitutional bodies created the Collegium System?",
        "answer": "Supreme Court through judgments",
        "choices": [
            "Supreme Court through judgments",
            "Parliament through amendment",
            "Law Commission of India",
            "National Judicial Appointments Commission"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Collegium for appointment of Supreme Court judges consists of:",
        "answer": "CJI + 4 senior-most SC judges",
        "choices": [
            "CJI + 4 senior-most SC judges",
            "CJI + 2 senior-most SC judges",
            "CJI + Law Minister + 2 senior-most SC judges",
            "President + CJI + Attorney General"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which case established the primacy of the Chief Justice of India and introduced the Collegium System?",
        "answer": "Second Judges Case (1993)",
        "choices": [
            "Second Judges Case (1993)",
            "First Judges Case (1981)",
            "Third Judges Case (1998)",
            "Kesavananda Bharati Case (1973)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The basic structure doctrine was established in which Supreme Court case?",
        "answer": "Kesavananda Bharati Case (1973)",
        "choices": [
            "Kesavananda Bharati Case (1973)",
            "Golaknath Case (1967)",
            "Minerva Mills Case (1980)",
            "Indira Sawhney Case (1992)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Collegium System was expanded to include a 5-member body in which case?",
        "answer": "Third Judges Case (1998)",
        "choices": [
            "Third Judges Case (1998)",
            "First Judges Case (1981)",
            "Second Judges Case (1993)",
            "Indira Gandhi v. Raj Narain (1975)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which judgment is called the “Election Case”, leading to the declaration of National Emergency in 1975?",
        "answer": "Indira Gandhi v. Raj Narain (1975)",
        "choices": [
            "Indira Gandhi v. Raj Narain (1975)",
            "First Judges Case (1981)",
            "Second Judges Case (1993)",
            "Third Judges Case (1998)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which case is famously known as the “Habeas Corpus Case” during the Emergency (1976)?",
        "answer": "ADM Jabalpur v. Shivkant Shukla (1976)",
        "choices": [
            "ADM Jabalpur v. Shivkant Shukla (1976)",
            "Maneka Gandhi v. Union of India (1978)",
            "Indira Gandhi v. Raj Narain (1975)",
            "Minerva Mills v. Union of India (1980)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Supreme Court is a ",
        "answer": "Final Interpreter of the Constitution",
        "choices": [
            "Final Interpreter of the Constitution",
            "Fedral Court",
            "Protector of Human Rights",
            "Civil Courts"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The current sanctioned strength of the Supreme Court of India is",
        "answer": "34 Judges",
        "choices": [
            "34 Judges",
            "30 Judges",
            "28 Judges",
            "24 Judges"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Supreme Court in India was established",
        "answer": "by the Indian Constitution",
        "choices": [
            "by the Indian Constitution",
            "by an act of Parliament in 1950",
            "under Indian Independence Act, 147",
            "under Indian Government Act, 1953"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Of the following statements, which one is not correct?",
        "answer": "Supreme Court can hear from any High Court / Tribunals except Court-martial",
        "choices": [
            "Supreme Court can hear from any High Court / Tribunals except Court-martial",
            "Supreme Court was constituted in 1950",
            "Supreme Court is the highest Court of appeal in the country",
            "Supreme Court can hear from any High Court/Tribunals as well as from Court-martial"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The power to increase the number of Judges in the Supreme Court of India is vested in",
        "answer": "The Parliament",
        "choices": [
            "The Parliament",
            "The President",
            "The Chief Justice of India",
            "The Law Commission"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who appoints the Judges of Supreme Court of India?",
        "answer": "The President",
        "choices": [
            "The President",
            "The Prime Minister",
            "The Chief Justice of India",
            "The Ombudsman"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the retirement age of the Judges of the Supreme Court?",
        "answer": "65 Years",
        "choices": [
            "65 Years",
            "62 Years",
            "60 Years",
            "64 Years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the retirement age of the Judges of the High Court?",
        "answer": "62 Years",
        "choices": [
            "62 Years",
            "65 Years",
            "60 Years",
            "70 Years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "A Judge of the Supreme Court may resign his office by writing to?",
        "answer": "The President",
        "choices": [
            "The President",
            "The Prime Minister",
            "The Law Minister",
            "The Attorney General of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The concept of Public Interest Litigation originated in the",
        "answer": "United States",
        "choices": [
            "United States",
            "United Kingdom",
            "India",
            "USSR"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who is the Constitutional Head of the State Governments?",
        "answer": "Governor",
        "choices": [
            "Governor",
            "Chief Minister",
            "Speaker",
            "High Court Judge"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Governor of a State is appointed by",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "The Chief Justice of the High",
            "The Chief Justice of India",
            "The Prime Minister"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "As per Indian Constitution, Legislature of States consits of",
        "answer": "Governor, Legislative Assembly and Legislative Council where it exists",
        "choices": [
            "Governor, Legislative Assembly and Legislative Council where it exists",
            "Legislative Assembly only",
            "Legislative Council only",
            "Governor and Legislative Council"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which is the Upper Chamber of State Legislatures in India?",
        "answer": "Legislative Council",
        "choices": [
            "Legislative Council",
            "Legislative Assembly",
            "Rajya Sabha",
            "Lok Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "In any State of India, Legislative Council can be created or can be abolished by",
        "answer": "the Parliament as per Resolution passed by the Legislative Assembly of the State",
        "choices": [
            "the Parliament as per Resolution passed by the Legislative Assembly of the State",
            "the Governor on the recommendation of the Council of Ministers",
            "The Parliament",
            "The President on the recommendation of the Governor of the State"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "If the Speaker of Legislative Assembly of a State wants to resign, he will give his resignation to",
        "answer": "Deputy-Speaker",
        "choices": [
            "Deputy-Speaker",
            "Chief Minister",
            "Governor",
            "President"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The members of a State Legislative Council are not chosen by which of the following categories of persons?",
        "answer": "Industrialists",
        "choices": [
            "Industrialists",
            "Members of the local bodies/panchayats",
            "Teachers",
            "Graduates"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The authority to determine the number of Judges in a High Court rests with which of the following entities:",
        "answer": "The President",
        "choices": [
            "The President",
            "The Chief Minister of the State",
            "The Prime Minister",
            "The Parliament"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "A High Court Judge addresses his letter of resignation to ",
        "answer": "The President",
        "choices": [
            "The President",
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "Chief Justice of High Court",
            "Governor of the State"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The mobile court in India is the brain child of",
        "answer": "APJ Abdul Kalam",
        "choices": [
            "APJ Abdul Kalam",
            "Rajeev Gandhi",
            "Justice Bhagwati",
            "Mrs Pratibha Patil"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Constitutional Amendment in India made Judiciary subservient of Parliament?",
        "answer": "42nd Amendment",
        "choices": [
            "42nd Amendment",
            "43rd Amendment",
            "40th Amendment",
            "44th Amendment"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year was Sarkaria Commission, empowered to recommend changes in Centre-State relations submitted its report?",
        "answer": 1983,
        "choices": [
            1983,
            1985,
            1984,
            1981
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The President can declare National Emergency on the basis of",
        "answer": "Armed Rebellion",
        "choices": [
            "Armed Rebellion",
            "External Aggression",
            "War",
            "All of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "According to which Article National Emergency may be declared by the president of India?",
        "answer": "Article 352",
        "choices": [
            "Article 352",
            "Article 370",
            "Article 371",
            "Article 395"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The proclamation of emergency at the first instance can be restricted to",
        "answer": "6 months",
        "choices": [
            "6 months",
            "3 months",
            "15 days",
            "One Year"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Mainly on whose advice the President's Rule is imposed in the State?",
        "answer": "Governor",
        "choices": [
            "Governor",
            "Chief Minister",
            "Legislative Assembly",
            "Chief Justice of High Court"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Under which one of the following Articles is the formation of Finance Commmission laid down?",
        "answer": "Article 280",
        "choices": [
            "Article 280",
            "Article 269",
            "Article 265",
            "Article 268"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Federal Finance Commission in India relates to",
        "answer": "Finances between States and the Centre",
        "choices": [
            "Finances between States and the Centre",
            "Finances among the States",
            "Finances between the Centre and Local Self Governments",
            "None of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "When was the Planning Commission established?",
        "answer": "15th March, 1950",
        "choices": [
            "15th March, 1950",
            "10th March, 1950",
            "16th March, 1951",
            "20th March, 1950"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following is the CEO of the NITI Aayog?",
        "answer": "BVR Subhramanyam",
        "choices": [
            "BVR Subhramanyam",
            "Amitabh Kant",
            "Cyrus Mistry",
            "Soumya Kanti Ghosh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the full form of NITI Aayog",
        "answer": "National Institution for Transforming India",
        "choices": [
            "National Institution for Transforming India",
            "National Internal Trade Information",
            "National Intellectual Training Institute",
            "None of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article in the Indian Constitution is related with the establishment of the Election Commission of India?",
        "answer": "Article 324",
        "choices": [
            "Article 324",
            "Article 148",
            "Article 342",
            "Article 325"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Constitutional Amendment Act has added new provisions related to cooperative societies in fundamental rights and DPSPs of the Constitution of India?",
        "answer": "97th Amendment",
        "choices": [
            "97th Amendment",
            "96th Amendment",
            "95th Amendment",
            "94th Amendment"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "A bill for the amendment in Indian Constitution can be presented",
        "answer": "either in Lok Sabha or Rajya Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "either in Lok Sabha or Rajya Sabha",
            "Only in Rajya Sabha",
            "Only in Lok Sabha",
            "In the Supreme Court of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "When was the first Bill for the amendment of the Indian Constitution presented?",
        "answer": 1951,
        "choices": [
            1951,
            1950,
            1955,
            1958
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Constitutional Amendment Acts was termed as Mini Constitution?",
        "answer": "42nd Amendment",
        "choices": [
            "42nd Amendment",
            "44th Amendment",
            "46th Amendment",
            "50th Amendment"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution prescribes Hindi in Devanagari script as the Official language of the Union?",
        "answer": "Article 343",
        "choices": [
            "Article 343",
            "Article 341",
            "Article 342",
            "Article 346"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The number of official languages recognised by the constitution in the eight schedule is",
        "answer": 22,
        "choices": [
            22,
            18,
            16,
            20
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which one of the following was established as the first programme of community development?",
        "answer": "National Extension Service",
        "choices": [
            "National Extension Service",
            "Cooperation Movement",
            "Integrated Rural Development Programme",
            "Har Ghar Nal ka Jal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The minimum age for contesting election to the Panchayati Raj Institutions is?",
        "answer": "21 years",
        "choices": [
            "21 years",
            "25 years",
            "18 years",
            "30 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Panchayati Raj was first introduced in",
        "answer": "Rajasthan",
        "choices": [
            "Rajasthan",
            "Andhra Pradesh",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Himachal Pradesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The decision to conduct Panchayat Elections is taken by which of the following?",
        "answer": "State Government",
        "choices": [
            "State Government",
            "Central Government",
            "District Judge",
            "Election Commission"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The subject of Panchayati Raj is in",
        "answer": "State List",
        "choices": [
            "State List",
            "Union List",
            "Concurrent List",
            "Residual List"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following functions is not the concern of Local Self-Government?",
        "answer": "Maintenance of Public Order",
        "choices": [
            "Maintenance of Public Order",
            "Public Health",
            "Sanitation",
            "Public Utility Services"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "73rd Amendment of the Constitution is related to",
        "answer": "Panchayati Raj System",
        "choices": [
            "Panchayati Raj System",
            "Impeachement of the President",
            "The appointment of the election commission",
            "Reservation of seats in educational institutions"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The legislative origins of the 73rd Constitutional Amendment Act can be traced back to which Constitutional Amendment Bill?",
        "answer": "64th Constitutional Amendment Bill",
        "choices": [
            "64th Constitutional Amendment Bill",
            "61st Constitutional Amendment Bill",
            "62nd Constitutional Amendment Bill",
            "63rd Constitutional Amendment Bill"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following was constituted under the Panchayati Raj System?",
        "answer": "Gram Panchayat",
        "choices": [
            "Gram Panchayat",
            "Khap Panchayat",
            "Caste Panchayat",
            "Jan Panchayat"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article of Indian Constitution directs state Government to organise village Panchayats?",
        "answer": "Article 40",
        "choices": [
            "Article 40",
            "Article 32",
            "Article 48",
            "Article 51"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Panchayti Raj is organised as a unit of self government under",
        "answer": "73rd Amendment of the Constitution",
        "choices": [
            "73rd Amendment of the Constitution",
            "Fundamental Rights of the Indian Constitution",
            "The preamble of the Indian Constitution",
            "Directive Principles of State Policy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the main characterstic of Panchayati Raj system of Government?",
        "answer": "All of these",
        "choices": [
            "All of these",
            "It has three tiers of Government",
            "It aims to give social and economic justice to villages",
            "Some members of Parliament are as representatives in Zila Parishad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "To review the financial position of Panchayats, the State Government constitutes every five years a/an",
        "answer": "Finance Commission",
        "choices": [
            "Finance Commission",
            "Finance Committee",
            "Advisory Commission",
            "Advisory Committee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Panchayati Raj is mainly aimed at",
        "answer": "Decentralisation of powers to villagers",
        "choices": [
            "Decentralisation of powers to villagers",
            "Increasing rivalry among villagers",
            "Giving training to villagers for contesting election",
            "increasing revenue from the villagers"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "For successful functioning, Panchayati Raj needs full co-operation of ",
        "answer": "Local Public",
        "choices": [
            "Local Public",
            "Central Government",
            "Bureuacrats",
            "Politicians"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Panchayati Raj in India represents",
        "answer": "Decentralisation of powers",
        "choices": [
            "Decentralisation of powers",
            "Participation of the people",
            "Community Development",
            "All of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which one of the following is not the characterstic of decentralisation?",
        "answer": "To instill non-confidence among local communities",
        "choices": [
            "To instill non-confidence among local communities",
            "Autonomy",
            "People's participation",
            "to empower local communities"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Name the Committee which was set up by the NDC in 1957 for the reorganisation of CDP and NES, which suggested a three-tier system of rural local government",
        "answer": "Balwant Rai Mehta Committee",
        "choices": [
            "Balwant Rai Mehta Committee",
            "Ashok Mehta Committee",
            "Maharashtra Committee on Democratic Decentralisation",
            "Rural-Urban Relationship Committee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Chairman of the Committee set up for the recommendation of Panchayati Raj in India was",
        "answer": "Balwant Rai Mehta",
        "choices": [
            "Balwant Rai Mehta",
            "BR Ambedkar",
            "Jagjivan ram",
            "Justice Krishna Ayer"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Panchayati Raj System was first started in India in the State of Rajasthan and ",
        "answer": "Andhra Pradesh",
        "choices": [
            "Andhra Pradesh",
            "Haryana",
            "Gujarat",
            "Uttar Pradesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Decentralisation System was recommended by",
        "answer": "Balwant Rai Mehta",
        "choices": [
            "Balwant Rai Mehta",
            "C Rajagopalachari",
            "JB Kriplani",
            "Ashok Mehta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Ashok Mehta Committee recommended how many tiers of Panchayati Raj",
        "answer": "Two-tier",
        "choices": [
            "Two-tier",
            "Thre-tier",
            "Single-tier",
            "Multiple-tier"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which one of the following Committees/Commissions recommended the creation of Nyaya Panchayats?",
        "answer": "Ashok Mehta Committee",
        "choices": [
            "Ashok Mehta Committee",
            "Balwant Rai Mehta Committee",
            "GVK Rao Committee",
            "Sarkaria Comission"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Constitutional Amendement granted Constitutional status to Panchayati Raj Institutions?",
        "answer": "73rd Amdendment",
        "choices": [
            "73rd Amdendment",
            "71st Amendment",
            "70th Amritsar",
            "75th Amendment"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which Article gives the list of 29 functions to be performed by the Panchayati Raj Institutions?",
        "answer": "Article 243(G)",
        "choices": [
            "Article 243(G)",
            "Article 243(H)",
            "Article 243(F)",
            "Article 243(E)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which was the first state in India to provide 50% reservation for women in Panchayati Raj Institutions?",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Madhya Prades"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The three-tier system of Panchayati Raj consits of ",
        "answer": "Gram Panchayat, Panchayat Samiti, Zila Parishad",
        "choices": [
            "Gram Panchayat, Panchayat Samiti, Zila Parishad",
            "Gram Panchayat, Panchayat Samit, Block Samiti",
            "Gram Panchayat, Block Samiti, Zila Parishad",
            "Block Samiti, Zila Parishad, Panchayat Samiti"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "A Panchayat Samiti at the block level in India is only a/an",
        "answer": "Administrative Authority",
        "choices": [
            "Administrative Authority",
            "Advisory Body",
            "Consultative Committee",
            "Coordinating and Supervisory Authority"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which is not among the powers of Panchayati Raj Insititutions in India?",
        "answer": "Judicial Review",
        "choices": [
            "Judicial Review",
            "Implementation of Land Reforms",
            "Implementation of Poverty Allevation Programmes",
            "Sanitation"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following is land record officer?",
        "answer": "Patwari",
        "choices": [
            "Patwari",
            "Lambardar",
            "Zamindar",
            "Zaildar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "At what level does a Panchayat Samiti operate a Panchayati Raj structure?",
        "answer": "Block-level body",
        "choices": [
            "Block-level body",
            "District Level",
            "Gram Panchayat Level",
            "State Level"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The National Human Rights Commission was set up in which year?",
        "answer": 1993,
        "choices": [
            1993,
            1992,
            2003,
            1983
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The right to Information in India is",
        "answer": "Fundamental Right",
        "choices": [
            "Fundamental Right",
            "Legal Right",
            "Social Right",
            "Directive Principle of State Policy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who of the following was the Prime Minister of the country at the time of the formation of Mandal Commission in India?",
        "answer": "Morarji Desai",
        "choices": [
            "Morarji Desai",
            "Chaudhari Charan Singh",
            "VP Singh",
            "Indira Gandhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following headed the two Boundary Commission set up to delineate the international frontiers between India and Pakistan in 1947?",
        "answer": "Cyril Radcliffe",
        "choices": [
            "Cyril Radcliffe",
            "Henry McMahon",
            "AP Moon",
            "AV Alexander"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Sikkim became a full-fledged State of the Union of India in",
        "answer": 1975,
        "choices": [
            1975,
            1974,
            1976,
            1977
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was the Chairman of the First Law Commission in Independent India?",
        "answer": "MC Setalvad",
        "choices": [
            "MC Setalvad",
            "JL Kapur",
            "VK Sunadaram",
            "TV Venkatarama Aiyar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Aritcle 300 of the Indian Constitution deal with",
        "answer": "Suits and Proceedings",
        "choices": [
            "Suits and Proceedings",
            "Government Contracts",
            "Attorney General",
            "Restriction on trade and commerce"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The division of each State into territorial constituencies for the Lok Sabha is done by Delimitation Commission. This delimitation has been freezed till which year?",
        "answer": 2026,
        "choices": [
            2026,
            2027,
            2025,
            2028
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Amnesty International is an organisation associated with",
        "answer": "Protection of Human Rights",
        "choices": [
            "Protection of Human Rights",
            "Protection of Women's Right",
            "Abolition of Untouchability",
            "Protection of Animal Rights"
        ]
    }
]